Guide to the Nadia Sablin Photographs, 2008-2014 RL.11035
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nadia Sablin photographs
2008-2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sablin, Nadia
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11035
1.5 Linear Feet 39 13x19 photographs in one box.
This collection includes 39 photographic prints comprising the series Aunties, by Nadia Sablin, the 2014 CDS/Honickman First Book Prize in Photography Award Winner. Aunties is a series of photographs detailing the lives of two unmarried sisters living in a Russian village.
Photographer's Biography
Nadia Sablin, a native of Russia, earned a B.F.A. from the Rochester Institute of Technology in 2002 and an M.F.A. from Arizona State University in 2011. A freelance photographer based in Brooklyn, New York, Sablin’s work has been featured in such publications as the New York Times, the Guardian, the Moscow Times, Slate, American Photo, the Calvert Journal, and WPO’s The Magazine. Sablin has received the Firecracker Photographic Grant, a New York Foundation for the Arts fellowship, a Puffin Foundation Grant, and was named one of the Magenta Foundation’s Emerging Photographers in 2011 as well as Sean O’Hagan’s Juror’s Pick for the Daylight Photo Awards in 2013. Sablin’s photographs have been seen in solo and group exhibitions across the U.S., including the Philadelphia Museum of Art, the Southeast Museum of Photography, the Cleveland Museum of Art, Blue Sky Gallery in Oregon, and Texas Women’s University School of Art.
About the CDS/ Honickman First Book Prize in Photography: North American photographers who are pursuing work of creative or social importance have too few opportunities for support and recognition; this is especially true when photographers are engaged in personal or in-depth ongoing projects. And while there are other sources for grants and fellowships in photography, the chance to see a body of work in print, as a coherent book-length work, is rare. Concerned about these problems and recognizing their shared organizational interests, the Honickman Foundation and the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University came together to create this important biennial book-publication prize, first awarded in 2002.
The prize is open to North American photographers who use their cameras for creative exploration, whether it be of places, people, or communities; of the natural or social world; of beauty at large or the lack of it; of objective or subjective realities. The prize honors work that is visually compelling, that bears witness, and that has integrity of purpose.
Judges for the First Book Prize in Photography are among the most significant and innovative artists, curators, and writers in contemporary photography: Robert Adams, Maria Morris Hambourg, Robert Frank, Mary Ellen Mark, William Eggleston, and Deborah Willis.
Winners of the CDS/Honickman First Book Prize in Photography receive a grant of $3,000, publication of a book of photography, published by Duke University Press and the Center for Documentary Studies, and inclusion in a website devoted to presenting the work of the prizewinners. Winners also receive a solo exhibit—-beginning with the 2014 prize, at Duke University’s new Rubenstein Library Photography Gallery—-after which the photographs are placed in the library’s Archive of Documentary Arts.
Sandra S. Philips selected Nadia Sablin to win the seventh biennial competition in 2014 for her body of photographs that have been published Aunties by Duke University Press and CDS Books of the Center for Documentary Studies.
More information about the CDS/Honickman First Book Prize: http://firstbookprizephoto.com/
Collection Overview
Sablin's description: "Aunties is a series of photographs detailing the lives of two unmarried sisters living in a Russian village. Alevtina and Ludmila are in their seventies, but carry on the traditional way of life, chopping wood for heating the house, bringing water from the well, and making their own clothes. Vegetables they harvest in the fall and berries they gather in the summer supplement the meager pensions on which the elderly subsist in Russia. My photographs of them are a meditation on aging, family and a sense of belonging. The house in which the sisters live was built by their father, the rugs woven by their mother. They contribute to the home as well, with new wallpapers, hand-sewn curtains, quilts and lace. Folded handwritten recipes contain seeds for planting, or rolled up balls of stray hair. Their environment is as much a character as they are themselves."
The collection consists of 39 13"x19" color photographs printed on Epson Exhibition Fiber Paper.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection was acquired in 2015 as a gift.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection
Documentary Photography -- Russia; Russians; Sablin, Nadia; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
- 1. Lucia with Scythe, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2. Planks for a New Fence, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 3. At the Sawmill, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 4. Black Currants, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 5. Still Life with Onion Flower Buds, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 6. Still Life with Threads, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 7. Sheets in the Attic, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 8. Sudoku, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 9. Lucia Walking to the Cemetery, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 10. Alia in the Attic, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 11. Onions, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 12. Vegetable garden, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 13. Still Life with Clock and Radio, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 14. Berries and Sugar, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 15. Fallen Apples, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 16. Kingdom under the Apple Tree, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 17. Dandelion Crown, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 18. Alia in the Kitchen, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 19. Favourite Soap, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 20. The Last Strawberries, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 21. Lucia in the Attic, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 22. After Banya, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 23. Red Apples, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 24. Alia Embroidering, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 25. Lucia, Unbraided, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 26. Kitchen at Sunset, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 27. Alevtina and Ludmila with Blueberries, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 28. Lucia in the Forest, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 29. Still Life with Glasses and Eraser, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 30. Alia, Braiding, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 31. Waiting for Lucia, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 32. Raincoats, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 33. Broken fence, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 34. Saw Two, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 35. After Supper, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 36. Lunch for Two, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 37. Lucia, resting, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 38. A six letter word for…, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 39. Lucia Cleaning Up, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 8)